<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God's revenge against murther demonstrated in the apprehension, prosecution &amp; execution of Henry Symbal and William Jones, for the inhumane murther of Richard Sandford Baronet, murthered by them the 8th of Septemb., 1675.</title>
            <author>Tonge, John, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16840</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12599468</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12599468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64124</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62926)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64124)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 676:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God's revenge against murther demonstrated in the apprehension, prosecution &amp; execution of Henry Symbal and William Jones, for the inhumane murther of Richard Sandford Baronet, murthered by them the 8th of Septemb., 1675.</title>
                  <author>Tonge, John, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Cademan ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Tonge. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sandford, Richard, --  Sir, d. 1675.</term>
               <term>Symbal, Henry, d. 1675.</term>
               <term>Jones, William, d. 1675.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64124:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64124:1"/>
            <p>GOD'S REVENGE AGAINST <hi>MURTHER,</hi> Demonſtrated in the Apprehenſion, Proſecution &amp; Execution OF <hi>HENRY SYMBAL</hi> AND <hi>WILLIAM JONES,</hi> For the Inhumane MURTHER of Sir Richard Sandford Baronet, Murthered by them the 8th of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1675.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>William Cademan,</hi> at the Popes-Head in the <hi>New Exchange</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64124:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64124:2"/>
            <head>To the Honorable and truly Vertuous Lady, Dame Mary Sandford, Relict of Sir <hi>RICHARD SANDFORD</hi> of <hi>Howgil</hi>-Caſtle in the County of <hi>Weſtmorland</hi> Bar.</head>
            <head>The Author moſt humbly Dedicates the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing LINES.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Cannot think the enſuing Relation will be acceptable to your Ladyſhip; for it is an Accompt of the Barbarous Murther of your late dear Husband. Your ſenſe of the loſs you have not only demonſtrated in your large and bountifull acknowledgments of your thankfullneſs to ſuch as you found were inſtrumentall in bringing his Murderes to condign Puniſhment, but much more by your thus long ſequeſtring your ſelf from the Pleaſures and Enjoyments of the
<pb facs="tcp:64124:3"/>World, continuing in the diſconſolate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a Widow, like the chaſt Turtle, ſtill mourning for the loſs of him whom it is impoſsible to recal; whilſt your virtue, Humility, ſweet Aſpect, and reſplendent Beauty, render your Ladyſhip, not only deſired, but admired by all that know you.</p>
            <p>Thus throwing my ſelf at your Lady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Feet, humbly begging pardon for this my preſumption, I beſeech God to bleſs you, and to give you Comfort in your two ſweet Babes, the choice pledges of that Conjugal Affection that was betwixt your dear Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and your ſelf; and that you may af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all the Enjoyments and ſatisfactions of this World, have the eternal Bliſs of that to come; which ſhall be the conſtant deſire of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant, <hi>JOHN TONGE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64124:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>GENTLE READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is probable thou wilt Admire why this Narrative, after it had lain ſo long quiet, ſhould throng to the Preſs, at this time ſo full, and croud it ſelf into the World. I can aſſure thee that it is not the Authors am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition to be ſeen in Print that cauſed this publication, but ſome late diſcourſes whereby the aſhes of the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Sir <hi>Richard Sandford,</hi> ſeemed Irreverently to be raked and drawn out of his Tomb, and therewith the Reputation of the Proſecutor trampled upon; as if he had with too much ſeverity proſecuted the Offenders, and by an overcuning management of the Evidence brought againſt them, drawn them rather to ſpeake his ſenſe, than their own words, whereby the Court was brought to Judge worſe of the Priſoners than the fact did truly and in its ſelf merit; for which perſuaſion there was no other inducement then <hi>Symball</hi>'s falſe pretence at his
<pb facs="tcp:64124:4"/>Tryall, that he kill'd Sir <hi>Richard</hi> fairely, and at the Gibbet, that he fonght him in his own defence.</p>
            <p>In theſe Particulars, that Friends may be ſatisfied who deſire it, the Ignorant undeceived, the Proſecutor juſtified, and the Court vindicated, to whom it was fully demonſtrated that both thoſe ſuggeſtions were ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly falſe, and that they did baſely and ſecretly fall upon Sir <hi>Richard</hi> in the dark, and without ſpeaking any word of warning till he had received his death. Tho' man may be deceived, God will not be mocked, who ſaith, <hi>Vengance is mine, and I will repay it;</hi> I am ſure nothing is more plain then that Gods Juſtice hath ſhowed it ſelf eminently in this Caſe, by prompting and directing the Proſecutor, as it were by Divine impulſe or inſpiration more then once in this affair: when falſe tricks and cheats were ſtrongly endeavoured to be impoſed upon his belief, to let him in the proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, he was made ſee them to he ſuch beyond any natural ſagacity; ſo alſo in defeating them, and over taking them in their craft, notwithſtanding their often croſſing the Roads, and making falſe pretences of going one way, when indeed they went another, inquiring for places which when out of ſight, they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely ſhunned, and went the quite contrary way, hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby to amuſe the Perſuer.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64124:4"/>
            <p>As for the Tryall, the matter of fact appeared ſo clear, that both the Judges and all the Jury were fully ſatisfied that it was a Barbarous Murder; and I doubt not but that all uninterſted perſons, who ſhall peruſe the following diſcourſe, will plainly ſee the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the contrary pretenſes.</p>
            <p>To thoſe who are pleaſed to ſay, <hi>tho' all were true, they would not have had their hands in their blood:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Proſecuter for anſwer to ſuch nice ſcrupuloſity ſaith, that he is very well ſatisfied in his Conſcience that he is innocent of their blood, who were ſo notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly guilty of Sir <hi>Richard</hi>'s; and he doubts not at the great Aſſize to be cleared of theirs by the Judge of all, who for his warrant hath enacted, <hi>that he that ſheds mans blood, by man his blood ſhall be ſhed;</hi> and taught us, that innocent blood cries to Heaven for vengeance.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:64124:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64124:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>God's Revenge againſt Murther:</head>
            <p>ON Wedneſday the 8th of <hi>September.</hi> 1675. Sir <hi>Rich: Sandford</hi> and Captain <hi>George Hilton</hi> went into <hi>Southwarke</hi> about Buſineſs, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to take water at the <hi>Beare</hi> at the <hi>Bridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot,</hi> being at the water ſide, they went into a Little Room, and called for a bottle of Wine, and before it was out, there came two or three boats full of Gentlemen, who landed at the <hi>Beare</hi> ſtares, ſeveral of whom were of Capt. <hi>Hiltons</hi> acquaintance, who (ſeeing him,) called him, and asked him how he did, upon which Sir <hi>Richard</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to one of them, the Gentlemen all going into a room cloſe by that, which Sir <hi>Richard</hi> and Capt. <hi>Hilton</hi> were in <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Making a Boul of Punch, ſeveral of them came to Sir <hi>Richard</hi> and Capt. <hi>Hilton,</hi> and deſired them to come into their Room, and to taſt their Liquor; but it being a Drink, that neither Sir <hi>Richard,</hi> nor Capt. <hi>Hilton</hi> did like, Sir <hi>Richard</hi> called for a Bottle of Wine, and ſtaying a Little while with them, one of the Company hearing Sir <hi>Richard</hi>'s name, took acquaintance with him upon the account of Sir <hi>Edward Stradling,</hi> but Sir <hi>Richard</hi>'s occaſions calling him away, (having appointed Buſineſs in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet</hi>) he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know where he might meet with that Gentleman and one friend more in the Evening, that then they might in a Glaſs of Wine Remember Sir <hi>Edward Stradling,</hi> and they agreed to meet at the ſigne of the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>White-Fryars.</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64124:6"/>Then Sir <hi>Richard,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Hilton</hi> took leave of the Company and went a bout their concerns, and at the time appointed they came to the <hi>George,</hi> and preſently after them, came one <hi>Henry Symbal</hi> (who had been of the former Company) but a man altogether unknown either to Sir <hi>Richard,</hi> or Capt. <hi>Hilton,</hi> nor ever ſeen by either of them before that day) and with him one <hi>William Jones,</hi> another of the former Company, altogether a ſtranger to Sir <hi>Richard,</hi> but had ſome accquaintance with Capt. <hi>Hilton,</hi> theſe two enquired for the Gentlemen, which Sir <hi>Richard</hi> had appointed to meet him there, and were ſhowed up into the Room where Sir <hi>Richard,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Hilton</hi> were; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meadiately after whom came the Gentleman, and his friend whom Sir <hi>Richard</hi> had appointed to meet, and ſtayed two hours, then Sir <hi>Richard</hi> called for a reckoning (which being paid) the Gentleman and his friend went away. The reſt ſtayed to drink a bottle of Wine, then upon the table, and paid for in the reckning, they being gone, <hi>Jones</hi> asked <hi>Hilton</hi> for Box and Dice, who anſwered that he never played, and ſo had no occaſion to carry any, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Jones</hi> replyed, your Brother <hi>John</hi> oweth me Forty eight Shillings, Do you pay it me? and upon <hi>Hiltons</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal <hi>Jones</hi> threatned him, and came from Threats to Blows, and ſtruck him with a Caine, and ſo they fel a ſcufling, Sir <hi>Richard</hi> going to part them, <hi>Symbal</hi> layd hold on him, and would not ſuffer him to do it; then Sir <hi>Richard</hi> went to the ſtairs head to call ſome of the Houſe to part them; but <hi>Symbal</hi> Drew his Sword and ſtood in the door of the Chamber and would ſuffer none to go in, the Candles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, Sir <hi>Richard</hi> called for more, a ſervant-maid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up with them ſaw <hi>Hilton</hi> down upon the flower, and <hi>Jones</hi> upon him Beating him, and Sir <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Symbal</hi> ſtanding with their Swords drawn, and Sir <hi>Richa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> faſt hold of <hi>Symbals</hi> Sword hand, and <hi>Symbal</hi> faſt hold of his,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64124:6"/>Sir <hi>Richard</hi> ſtriving to go to part <hi>Hilton</hi> and <hi>Jones,</hi> and the other endeavouring to keep him from doing it, but a Conſtable being called, <hi>Jones</hi> let <hi>Hilton</hi> riſe, and ſo when they were parted, Sir <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Hilton</hi> went down ſtairs, and Sir <hi>Richard</hi> went quite out of the doors, but <hi>Jones</hi> laid hold of <hi>Hilton,</hi> as he was going out, and ſaid he would make him pay for Glaſſes that were Broke in the ſcuffel, and ſo ſtopping of him, Sir <hi>Richard</hi> came back to ſee why he ſtayed, and taking <hi>Hilton</hi> by the hand, they went a way together, leaving <hi>Symbal</hi> and <hi>Jones</hi> in the Tavern, and when Sir <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Hilton</hi> were gone, <hi>Jones</hi> ſwore <hi>Dam him,</hi> he would do both their Buſineſs that night. And having got two more of their Comrades to them, they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly perſued Sir <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Hilton,</hi> that were going down towards the water ſide, to take Boat, who hearing ſome follow them very faſt, apprehending that it might be <hi>Symbal</hi> and <hi>Jones,</hi> with their Comrades whom <hi>Hilton</hi> ſaw in the Tavern before he came forth of it; they ſtept into a little alley to avoide them, but <hi>Symbal</hi> perſuing them cloſer then the reſt, Diſcovering them, called to <hi>Jones,</hi> and ſaid, They are here: ſo ſending their Comrades a little before them down the Street, they came to the Alley-end; which Sir <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Hilton</hi> ſeeing, leaſt they ſhould be ſet upon in the ſtreight-Alley, made haſt to come forth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtreet, <hi>Symbal</hi> ſtanding at the Corner in the dark, as Sir <hi>Richard</hi> came forth, ran his Sword into his Left ſide, under the ſhort Ribs, up into the ſtomach and thorough the midriffe into the Back-bone, from which he could ſcarce pull it back again, ſaying wil't pay the Eight and forty ſhillings or not? at the ſame time <hi>Jones,</hi> with his Sword drawn, made at <hi>Hilton,</hi> and ſaid this is my man, giving him ſeveral Cuts over the head, Sir <hi>Richard</hi>'s Sword being in his ſcabbard, he ſtepping back to draw, ſtaggered, and ſaid, I am ſlain, at which <hi>Jones</hi> looking about, gave <hi>Hilton</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64124:7"/>time to draw his Sword, Sir <hi>Richard</hi> at the ſame time draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, endeavoured to defend himſelf, but having Received one wound more in his right ſide, and another in his right ſhoulder, and his Caul comeing forth at his wound he had Received on his left ſide, he not being able to ſtand any longer, ſtaggered bewixt <hi>Symbal</hi> and <hi>Jones;</hi> and then <hi>Symbal</hi> Joyned with <hi>Jones</hi> againſt <hi>Hilton,</hi> and their two Comrades (that were going from them) hearing the noiſe, one of them came, and laid hold of <hi>Hiltons</hi> Sword-hand, at which time <hi>Symbal</hi> run <hi>Hilton</hi> through his Left ſide, into his Lungs, then both <hi>Symbal</hi> and <hi>Jones</hi> with their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rades fled; this was done betwixt nine and ten of the Clock in the evening. And Sir <hi>Richard</hi> Lived in Great Torment, untill almoſt ten of the Clock the next morning. And finding it Impoſſible for him to ſurvive, he declared to the Proſecutor, and to ſeveral others, that he Received that wound in his left ſide, (which was his mortal wound) from <hi>Symbal,</hi> and that he gave him it unawars, when his Sword was in his ſcabbard at his ſide, and without any manner of Provocation. Sir <hi>Richard</hi> being dead, and the Coroner being ſent for, Bound a Gentleman a friend of Sir <hi>Richards,</hi> who was with him when he Died, to make Proſecution, and ſummoning a Jury, the inqueſt found it Murther in <hi>Symbal,</hi> and <hi>Jones</hi> Aiding, Aſſiſting, Abetting, Concurring and Comforting in the ſaid Murther. Whilſt the Coroners In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt was ſitting, the Proſecutor came into one of the rooms of the Houſe, where they were to ſpeak with ſome of the witneſſes, he met there with one that he never had ſeen before, and fancied that it might be one of Sir <hi>Richards</hi> Murtherers, and going to take a ſtrict view of him, the party ſeemd to be ſhie of him, it Confirmed him in his opinion that it muſt be one of the four that perſued Sir <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Hilton,</hi> after their going out of the Tavern, and the Proſecutor going to ſpeak with a Gentleman in the room, could not forbear obſerving
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64124:7"/>the ſtranger, who took the opportunity of the ſlipping down ſtairs, when he ſaw the Proſecutor buſie, which he ſeeing, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and comeing to him, deſired to know his name, but he denying to tell it the Proſecutor, ſeiſed him, and ſecured him, and knowing that ſome in the houſe did know if he were one of the four Perſuers, had two Examined upon oath, who both confeſſed they did know him, and that he was one of them, after which he confeſt it himſelf, and that he was the man that held <hi>Hilton</hi> by the Sword-hand, when <hi>Symbal</hi> gave him the wound in his left ſide. Then the Proſecutor made it his Buſineſs to find out the reſt of the Murtherers, and being in St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Parke,</hi> conſidering with himſelf, what courſe was beſt to be taken for the Apprehending them, immediately he eſpyed comeing into the <hi>Park,</hi> ſeveral perſons which he knew to be <hi>Jone</hi>'s Companions, upon ſight of whom, it came into his mind, that ſeveral of theſe being neceſſitous, it was probable that for a ſum of money ſome of them would diſcover to him where the Murtherers were, or at leaſt tell them his Propoſals, and hoped it might chance to fright them out of the Town, and then he did believe, that he ſhould have them taken. Being much moved with this Perſwaſion, he ſtepd in amongſt them, and openly declared that he was the Proſecutor of <hi>Symbal</hi> and <hi>Jones,</hi> and that he would give Ten pounds Reward to any that would ſecure <hi>Symbal</hi> or <hi>Jones,</hi> and Twenty pounds for the ſecuring of them both, or to any that would inform him where they were, and aſſiſt him in the ſecuring of them, that he did intend to publiſh this reward in the next Gazette. The next day ſeveral came, and promiſed the Proſecutor, that if he would get the Lord Chiefe Juſtice his Warrant, he ſhould have the Murtherers ſecured, for the Reward promiſed; upon which, the Chief Juſtie not being in Town, he procured a Warrant from one of the Judges of the Kings-Bench; and ſo meeting the perſons at the place appointed, upon Diſcourſe with them found that their Pretentions were
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64124:8"/>nothing but Air, and he leaning upon his Arm to conſider of the matter, immediately thought with himſelf the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers were certainly fled, and that theſe people were ſet on work with deſign to Amuze him, and cauſe him to ſpend his time and money whileſt the Murtherers might the more eaſily make their eſcape, he leaving a Friend or two with them to keep them Company, fancying that if the Murtherers were gone, a Gentleman of his acquaintance muſt know of their going, and be inſtrumental in aſſiſting them to make their eſcape; both which Suggeſtions proved true, though it was done without any other ground but his own Imagination. So going to enquire after that Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, he chanced into a Houſe where the Murtherers Lodged that very night they had committed the Fact, where he was told, That <hi>Symbal</hi> had received a wound in his Breaſt. (by knowledg of which, they were at <hi>Wallingford</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to the Perſuer) He meeting with the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man whom he went to look after, charged him poſitively with his aſſiſting the Murtherers in making their Eſcape, which though the Gentleman denied at firſt, yet after ſome time he ſaid they were gone, and that he had helped them away: The Proſecutor asked him which way they were gone, ſaying he reſolved to follow them; the other An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him that he had hired them an Oyſter Veſſel at <hi>Billingſgate</hi> (for ten Guineas) to carry them to <hi>Callis,</hi> and that they ſet Sail on Monday Morning betwixt four and five a Clock, and that he ſee them down the River, and ſaid he hoped they were in <hi>France</hi> by that time, which he ſaid to deceive the Proſecutor, that he might look no more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them. But the Proſecutor, as it were by Inſpiration, ſuſpecting the Truth of this plauſible Story, which moſt men would have been ſatisfied withal, told him perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily that he knew they were not gone that way, but over Land, and that if he would not Diſcover the Truth to him,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64124:8"/>he would take him before a Magiſtrate and Charge him with the Fact: and when he ſaw there was nothing but a Priſon for him, if he did not confeſs the Truth, rather than go to <hi>Newgate,</hi> he did acknowledg what he had ſaid was falſe, and that he did it on purpoſe to cauſe the Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor to forbear further Search, and that he did believe they were fled into the Country, but whither he knew not, for he left them at a Tavern on Sunday night in a great fear leſt they ſhould be diſcovered to the Proſecutor, who had promiſed ſuch a Reward for the Apprehending of them. And ſo the Proſecutor, ſatisfied with this, took the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man along with him, and went to the Tavern where they were on Sunday night, and that he might the better inform himſelf, he pretended to be <hi>Symbals</hi> Uncle, a Brewer, which he did, leaſt they knowing him to be the Proſecutor, ſhould not diſcover the Truth to him, and enquiring for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Houſe, he not being within, asked for his Wife, and told her that his name was <hi>Symbal,</hi> and that he was Uncle to that unfortunate young man, who it was ſaid had killed the Perſon of Quality in <hi>White Friars</hi> on Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday laſt at night, and that he had an account that Mr. <hi>Francis,</hi> the Maſter of that houſe, had been very civil to his Nephew and his Comrade, and had aſſiſted them to make their Eſcape, the particulars whereof he was come to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in from his own mouth, that he might better be able to acknowledg and gratifie the kindneſs done; for ſaid he if they be taken they are dead men. Upon which the Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Replied, <hi>We hear indeed that the Proſecutor is a very ſevere man, and will follow them very cloſe, but I hope they are now out of his way, for my Husband hired them a Coach and went with them to</hi> Barnet, <hi>and there ſold them a Mare, and hired them two Horſes and a Guide:</hi> But the Proſecutor asking which way they went from <hi>Barnet,</hi> ſhe Anſwered ſhe did not know, but her Husband would be within preſently, who would
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64124:9"/>give a better account: The Proſecutor ſitting down, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the Maſter of the Houſes return; and ſtaying there till ten of the Clock at Night, and the other not coming home, he was directed to go to the Sign of the Ship in the <hi>Old-Baily,</hi> and there the Proſecutor being known, was neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated to take his own name again, for finding <hi>Francis</hi> there, and being informed that he had been that day with <hi>Symbal</hi> the Brewer receiving money for the Mare that he had ſold the Murtherers, the Proſecutor going in, told <hi>Francis</hi> who he was, and charged him with aſſiſting the Murtherers to make their eſcape from him, and deſired <hi>Francis</hi> to let him know which way they were gone, that if poſſible he might find ſome means to Retrive them; but <hi>Francis</hi> denying that he knew any thing of them, and giving the Proſecutor ſcurrillous Language, he having neither Warrant nor Conſtable ready, he procured a Coach to be brought to the dore, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <hi>Francis</hi> into it, took him before a Juſtice of the Peace, who making his <hi>Mittimus</hi> to ſend him to <hi>Newgate,</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt his conveying them to <hi>Barnet,</hi> as is before deſcribed, and that they went away from <hi>London</hi> about four a Clock on Monday Morning the tenth day of <hi>September,</hi> and that at <hi>Barnet,</hi> beſides that they bought of him, they hired two Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes more, and a Guide, for two days Journey outward, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out naming any place they would go to, but gave Security for the return of the Guide and Horſes, upon the Thurſday night following, and upon the Wedneſday Morning the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor went to <hi>Barnet,</hi> and there he was informed that upon Monday in the Morning the Murtherers called at <hi>Gibbon,</hi> near <hi>Bel-bar,</hi> and enquired for one <hi>Cooke,</hi> who was lately come out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and was upon the returning thither again, but not meeting with him there, after ſome ſtay at the Sign of the <hi>Bell</hi> at <hi>Bel-bar,</hi> they proceeded on their Journey, and went to <hi>Hatfield,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Welling,</hi> and then croſſed the Countrey to <hi>Dunſtable,</hi> and kept that Road un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64124:9"/>they came to the Gibbit, two miles beyond <hi>Fenny-Strat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and then left that Road, croſſing the Country went through <hi>Whadden-chace</hi> to a little Town called <hi>Horrod,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Thame,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Wallingford,</hi> where they were Apprehended, and at firſt denied their names; but the Perſuer telling <hi>Symbal,</hi> that if he was not wounded in ſuch a place, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Breaſt, then he was not the man he did look after, and going to ſearch for the Wound, <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> did acknowledg he was the man, and confeſſed the Fact; from thence they were ſent to <hi>Reading</hi>-Goal, and by <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas Corpus</hi> removed to <hi>Newgate, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is worth Obſervation how they did croſs the Roads, one while as if they deſigned for the North, going that Road two Miles North of <hi>Welling,</hi> having pretended, as the Proſecutor was informed before he came out of <hi>London,</hi> to go to <hi>Stamford,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Boſton,</hi> and there take Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for <hi>Holland;</hi> but they croſſing the Country from <hi>Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> to <hi>Dunſtable,</hi> as if they deſigned for <hi>Weſtcheſter</hi> (which ſeemed to the Proſecutor very likely, they having told the Vintner that they would ſtay ſome time for <hi>Cooke</hi> at <hi>Bell-bar,</hi> and theire not only calling at <hi>Gibbon</hi> to enquire for <hi>Cook,</hi> who having married a Wife who had been formerly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant there, ſhe being then in <hi>Ireland,</hi> her Husband had been with her Miſtris and told her that about that time he intended to go into <hi>Jreland,</hi> to his wife, but they not finding him there, as they expected, they went to the ſign of the <hi>Bell</hi> at <hi>Bell-bar,</hi> and from thence, ſent ſeveral times to <hi>Gibben,</hi> to Enquire for <hi>Cooke,</hi>) followed that Road two miles <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>Fenney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratford,</hi> then croſſing the Country again into the <hi>Oxford</hi>-road, paſſed from thence to <hi>Wallingford,</hi> into the great Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern-road, and at ſeveral places they made motions of leaving the roads they took long before they left them; yet for all this Gods Vengeance did not let them ſlip, but ſtill Diſcovered their windings, and turnings, to the proſecutor,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64124:10"/>for providence tho' by a miſinformation lead him a far nearer way to them, then they went themſelves, and ſo they were Apprehended upon thurſday the 16 of <hi>September,</hi> before noon, and had their Tryal, upon Thurſday the fourteenth of <hi>October</hi> following at Juſtice-Hal in the <hi>Old-Baily London.</hi> And there it was proved in Court, that they did begin the Quarrel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of Provocation, and when the Judge asked them, what they could pretend was the cauſe of their Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, they were not able to make any appear. And it was further ſworn in Court that after Sir <hi>Richard</hi> and Capt. <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> had left the Tavern, <hi>Symbal</hi> and <hi>Jones</hi> ſtaying behind, having got ſome more of their Comrades to them, did threaten, (by ſwearing <hi>Dam em</hi>) they would do both their buſineſs that night, and then perſued them, and overtook them, and in the dark ſet upon them unawars, <hi>Jones</hi> falling upon <hi>Hilton,</hi> and it was likewiſe proved by a Gentleman of the Temple, and by the Proſecutor from Sir <hi>Richards</hi> own mouth, a little before he died, that <hi>Symbal</hi> came upon him at unawars, when his Sword was in it's ſcabbard at his ſide, and gave him his great wound in his left ſide; the ſame was ſworn by <hi>Hilton,</hi> who was an Eye witneſs to it; <hi>Jones</hi> being asked by a Friend if he did ſee Sir <hi>Richards</hi> Sword drawn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Symbal</hi> did paſs at him, anſwerd that <hi>Symbal</hi> had ſaid ſome things very ill at the Bar, but excuſed himſelf from making any poſitive Anſwer, ſaying that he fought <hi>Hilton</hi> with his back towards Sir <hi>Richard;</hi> yet <hi>Symbal</hi> had the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence (both upon his Tryal and Execution) to ſay that he fought Sir <hi>Richard</hi> fairly. I leave it to the Judgment of any man of ſenſe, whether it is not more reaſonable to believe Sir <hi>Richard Sandford</hi> dying (who was a Perſon of Honour of known worth and integrity) or his Murtherer, who hoped to mitigate his Fact in ſome peoples opinions, by endeavouring to impoſe a lye on the belief of thoſe that ſaw him a dying man?</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64124:10"/>
            <p>And that it may not ſeem ſtrange that I do thus endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to Juſtifie Sir <hi>Richard</hi> from his lying Tongue, I ſhall only take leave to give you an account what a fair fighter he was, and ſhall go no further then the Evidence ſworn in Court upon the Tryal. Firſt, <hi>Hilton</hi> ſwore that Sir <hi>Richard</hi> had his Sword in his Scabbard when <hi>Symbal</hi> gave him his mortal Wound, and that when Sir <hi>Richard</hi> was gone that <hi>Symbal</hi> joyned with <hi>Jones,</hi> who was then fighting with <hi>Hilton</hi> (which neither of them did deny) and that when a third man came in (who was one of their Comrades) and laid hold on <hi>Hilton</hi>'s Sword-hand, and held him faſt by it, that he could make no manner of defence, That then <hi>Symbal</hi> came and run him into the left ſide: the perſon that held <hi>Hilton</hi>'s Sword-hand confeſſed it to the Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and ſeveral others, and that he called out to <hi>Symbal</hi> to forbear puſhing at <hi>Hilton,</hi> being he had ſecured his Sword. And it was further ſworn by another, That upon Friday the third day of <hi>September</hi> 1675 (which was five days before this Murther was committed) <hi>Symbal</hi> and <hi>Jones</hi> going up the Street in <hi>White-Fryers,</hi> they met a Gentleman, upon whom <hi>Jones</hi> drew, and the Gentleman drawing in his defence, <hi>Symbal</hi> drew too, and joining with <hi>Jones,</hi> they both ſet upon him together; an Houſe-keeper ſtanding at his door, and ſeeing them, did at firſt believe they were in jeſt; but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they had villanouſly ſet upon the Gentleman, he took a Half-pike, and joined with the Gentleman, and ſo reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cued him from them; and upon his Oath in Court, ſaid, That he did believe, that they would have ſlain the Gentleman, if he had not come to his aſſiſtance. Several other of the like nature I could inſtance in; but having reſolved to go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the Evidence at Bar, I ſhall forbear, and only tell you how penitent <hi>Symbal</hi> was for the Murder, when he was apprehended at <hi>Wallingford</hi> After ſome demur, and falſifying his name, he did confeſs the Fact (as he pretended) with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64124:11"/>ſaying, That he was heartily ſorry for having ſlain that brave, worthy, and valiant Gentleman, Sir <hi>Richard Sandford;</hi> but wiſhed it had been <hi>Hilton;</hi> For then, ſaid he, I had not cared: as if it had not been as well Murder to have ſtab'd Captain <hi>Hilton</hi> baſely, as Sir <hi>Richard Sandford.</hi> Now that <hi>Symbal</hi> was a man who perſiſted in his Murtherous deſigns, is evident, partly by what hath been ſaid before, and likewiſe by a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his, writ (when in <hi>Reading</hi> Goal) to a Friend in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> which Letter was produced in Court, and there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be his hand, wherein he laments his own and his Friend <hi>Jones</hi>'s Misfortunes in being impriſoned; and imputes the cauſe of it to a Gentleman of his acquaintance, whom he chargeth (though falſly) to have betrayed them to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors; and ſaith, that he hopes that he hath ſome friend that will piſtol him piſſing againſt the Wall. For, ſaith he, he deſerves no better. All theſe things being proved, and the Murderers having nothing to alledge for themſelves, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indicted both upon the Statute of Stabbing, and at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law for Murder. The Jury withdrawing (in half a quarter of an hour) returned their Verdict, which was, that they found them both Guilty of both the Indictments, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly they received Sentence of Condemnation; and upon Friday the 22 of <hi>October</hi> they were hanged upon two Gibbets in <hi>Fleet-street, Symbal</hi> at the little Gate of <hi>VVhite-Fryers,</hi> and <hi>Jones</hi> at the great Gate, where they hung, by the Kings ſpecial Command, three hours, and were then taken down, and by the Kings Warrant, hung in Chains. <hi>Symbal</hi> at <hi>Stampford-Hill</hi> in the road near <hi>Totnam-Highcroſs. Jones</hi> upon <hi>Finchly-Common,</hi> betwixt <hi>Highgate</hi> and <hi>Barnet.</hi> And here I ſhall leave them to be an example to all Spectators of Gods juſt Judgment and Revenge againſt Murder; and give you an account of what is not unworthy your obſervation, how miraculouſly the Proſecutor, even by a falſe Information, hapned to find them. They having left <hi>Bel-bar,</hi> as is ſaid before, called at a little
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64124:11"/>houſe in <hi>Hatfield</hi> Road, at a Lane end, where a way lead to St. <hi>Albans,</hi> and asked the way thither, and took that way, as if they did intend to go to St. <hi>Albans,</hi> when out of the ſight of thoſe people, whom they inquired of, being well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the ways, they took a little By-lane that leads to <hi>Hatfield,</hi> and the Proſecutor believing that they were gone to St. <hi>Albans</hi> (that being the ready way to <hi>VVeſtcheſter,</hi> appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending they were flying for <hi>Ireland</hi>) took that way, and often asking at the houſes in the Lane-ſide, if the people did ſee ſuch men (deſcribing the perſons) ride that way; every one that he met with (by what diluſion I know not) affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that they ſee them paſs that way upon Monday in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon; and ſo all along until he came to St. <hi>Albans</hi> Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end, where he loſt all manner of account of them, as well he might; for they never came that way at all; ſo he (ſpending ſome time to inquire in St. <hi>Albans,</hi> whether they had been there or no; and getting no account of them) having loſt all manner of hopes to meet with them, unleſs at <hi>VVeſtcheſter,</hi> he took Poſt, deſigning for that place, but had ſcarce got out of the Towns-end, till hearing a Poſthorn wind, as he appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended one riding faſt after him, he ſtaid and found that it was one that followed him, on purpoſe to give him an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that the Murderers Guide was ſecured at St. <hi>Albans,</hi> who was returning with the Horſes that they had hired at <hi>Barnet;</hi> and this was occaſioned through the Proſecutors ſtrict enquiry and ſearch, which he made in that Town upon this lucky accident; the Proſecutor turning back to St. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bons,</hi> took their Guide away with him, who brought him to the place where they lay on Tueſday night; And here you may ſee how Gods providence did direct him in the queſt of theſe Murderers; for had he not been deceived by their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of going to St. <hi>Albans</hi> (when they had called at the little houſe at the Lanes end in <hi>Hatfield</hi> Road, where the people did inform that they were the ſame men that called
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64124:12"/>there, and went that way, that had ſtayed at the Sign of the <hi>Bell</hi> at <hi>Bel-bar,</hi> two or three hours upon Monday morning; and from thence ſent to <hi>Gibbon,</hi> by which he knew them to be the ſame that he followed) he had never gone to St. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans,</hi> and ſo had miſſed their Guide, and in all probability the Murderers had eſcaped.</p>
            <p>I ſhall cloſe the whole with a ſhort Character of <hi>Symbal,</hi> that was given the Proſecutor by a near Relation of his, (when he was in <hi>Newgate</hi>) who was extremely concerned for him, and would have been glad to have found the Fact ſuch as might have given hopes of ſaving his Kinſmans life, and to have had him tranſported; for the doing of which he would neither have ſpared pains, nor any thing elſe, (if the thing had been feazeable) but when he ſaw the uglineſs of the Murder made appear, he could not forbear admiring Gods Juſtice and Providence in following home ſo wicked a wretch as this his Kinſman was, lifting up his eyes and hands towards Heaven, he broke out into this grave and ſerious Meditation. <hi>Good God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou art wonderful in thy Providence, and in the Diſpenſations of thy Juſtice, towards this wicked young man; for I fear he ruin'd his Master; I'm ſure he broke the heart of his Mother, and ſold the Blood of his Father; and in thirteen years (ſince his Fathers death) I am a Thouſand pounds the worſe for him, and he is now cut off in the four and twentieth year of his age.</hi> I once more recommend it to the ſerious conſideration of all ſober and unbiaſſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whether it is more reaſonable to believe the dying words of Sir <hi>Richard Sandford,</hi> a Gentleman of Worth, and unſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reputation, or the words of his Murtherer (being a perſon of this Character) though upon the Gibbet.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:64124:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
